A Guide to the William E. Fulton Papers, 1889-1912
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
William E. Fulton Papers 1889-1912
Special Collections, Kegley Library
2007.2
15 folders.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Mary B. Kegley in 2007.
Historical Information
J. P. M. Sanders deeded most of his Grayson Sulphur Springs property to George T. Mills of Philadelphia in 1889, keeping only one-fourth acre for use by members of the Sanders, Fulton, Trigg, Currin, and Kincannon families. Mills subsequently sold the Springs in March 1890 to the Virginia Company, maintaining the original settlement of usage for the one-fourth acre.
The Virginia Company then conveyed part of the property to Norfolk & Western Railroad Company and part to Dr. J. L. Kernoodle of North Carolina.
After his purchase in 1897, North Carolina physician J. L. Kernoodle and his brother Dr. George W. Kernoodle and erected a new hotel at the Springs. The Springs proved to be a popular resort for visitors from near and far.
Legal entanglements ensued in 1911 when the New River Power Company sought to obtain usage of the one-fourth acre. William E. Fulton, J. Norment Powell, and Archer Phlegar represented members of the families who were part of Sanders's original agreement.
Scope and Content
The Papers consist of correspondence and legal records relating to the purchase and transfer of Grayson Sulphur Springs property in Carroll County, Virginia. Series I, Correspondence contains thirteen folders of correspondence between attorneys John Fulton and his brother William Edward Fulton and various clients. Series II contains legal records.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence. 1889-1912, 13 folders.
  - Folder 1. Correspondence. 1889-1895, 10 letters. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Correspondents include: Joseph B. Greever of Wartburg Seminary, attorney John H. Fulton, J. E. Caldwell of Wythe County Circuit Court, H. O. Rogers, S. C. Bralley, and H. M. Heuser.
  - Folder 2. Correspondence. 1896., 5 letters (Box-folder 1:2)
    Correspondents include: Joseph B. Greever of Wartburg Seminary and attorney John H. Fulton.
  - Folder 3. Correspondence. 1897., 8 letters. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Folder 4. Correspondence. 1902-1907, 5 letters. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Correspondents include: T. J. Hanson of Anchor and Hope Lot and Land Company, Andrew K. Fulton, William E. Hodges, Katherine Friel Graham, William E. Fulton, C. C. Tate of Bertha Mineral Company, and Sallie Tompkins.
  - Folder 5. Correspondence. 1909, 7 letters. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Correspondents include: D. H. Howard of Kirkpatrick & Howard and William E. Fulton.
  - Folder 6. Correspondence. May - 15 June 1911., 7 letters. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Correspondents include: William D. Tompkins, William E. Fulton, Dexter Goad of Carroll County Circuit Court, J. Norment Powell of Carolina, Clinchfield and Ohio Railway, and D. W. Bolen.
  - Folder 7. Correspondence. 16 June 1911 - 27 June 1911., 4 letters. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Correspondents include: Robert E. Scott of Buchanan and Caldwell, William E. Fulton, D. W. Bolen, and J. Norment Powell of Carolina, Clinchfield and Ohio Railway.
  - Folder 8. Correspondence. July 1911., 4 letters. (Box-folder 1:8)
    Correspondents include: William E. Fulton, Cyrus Phibbs, and Robert Scott of Buchanan and Caldwell.
  - Folder 9. Correspondence. August - September 1911., 5 letters. (Box-folder 1:9)
    Correspondents include: Robert Scott of Buchanan and Caldwell, William E. Fulton, J. Norment Powell of Carolina, Clinchfield and Ohio Railway, and W. H. Bolling.
  - Folder 10. Correspondence. August - September 1911., 7 letters. (Box-folder 1:10)
    Correspondents include: A. F. Green, William E. Fulton, Archer A. Phlegar, J. Norment Powell of Carolina, Clinchfield and Ohio Railway, and William D. Tompkins.
  - Folder 11. Correspondence. December 1911., 4 letters. (Box-folder 1:11)
    Correspondents include: William E. Fulton and Archer A. Phlegar.
  - Folder 12. Correspondence. February - September 1912., 5 letters. (Box-folder 1:12)
    Correspondents include: William E. Fulton, Archer A. Phlegar, Jonathan S. Draper, and J. Norment Powell of Phlegar, Price & Shelton.
  - Folder 13. Correspondence. October - December 1912, undated., 8 letters. (Box-folder 1:13)
    Correspondents include: J. Norment Powell of Phlegar, Price & Shelton, William E. Fulton, and Archer A. Phlegar.
- Series II. Legal Records. 1889 - 1911., 2 folders.
  - Folder 1. Deeds. 1889-1897., 5 deeds.
    Folder contains deeds: 5 October between J. P. M. Sanders, Andrew K. Fulton, Sallie W. Curran, Mary A. Trigg, A. N. Kincannon, and Archie W. Kincannon of the first part and George T. Mills of the second part; 8 March 1890 between George T. Mills and Josephine Mills of the first part and Virginia Company of the second part; 20 April 1890 between Virginia Company of the first part and Norfolk & Western Railroad of the second part; 18 August 1891 between Virginia Company of the first part, John W. Hamer of the second part, Joseph I. Doran and Ida W. Doran of the third part, and Norfolk and Western Railroad of the fourth part; 29 December 1897 between Virginia Company of the first part, John W. Hamer of the second part, Penn Mutual Life Insurance of the third part, Joseph I. Doran and Ida W. Doran of the fourth part, and J. L. Kernoodle of the fifth part.
  - Folder 2. Legal Records. 1911, undated, 2 items.
    Folder contains petition dated 30 October 1911 by New River Power Company to erect dam near Grayson Sulphur Spring; answer prepared by counsel of Phlegar, Powell, price and Shelton to Circuit Court of Pulaski County in case of New River Power Company vs. J. L. Kernoodle, undated.